Guide to the Elizabeth MacKinstry Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Elizabeth MacKinstry collection
1904-1957
1924-1934
YCAL MSS 408
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.0
(4 boxes)
The collection contains work by Elizabeth MacKinstry: autograph and typescript versions of poems, a set of illustrations for the children's book Eliza and the Elves, by Rachel Field (New York: Macmillan Company, 1926), and a scrapbook of her original and printed artwork dating from 1924-1934. One volume of poems was bound by John F. Grabau of Buffalo, New York, for MacKinstry's presentation to Emily Howland Leeming Lyman. Also present is a published volume of MacKinstry's poems, Helen's Mirror and Other Verses (London: Elkin Mathews, 1913), issued under her pseudonym Elizabeth Westermain.
MacKinstry, E. (Elizabeth)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Florence E. Brooks, 1956. Gift of Elizabeth Leeming Rose, 1970.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Yale Collection of American Literature Letter Collection (YCAL MSS 446), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Elizabeth Conkling MacKinstry (1878-1956)
Elizabeth MacKinstry, American poet, illustrator, and sculptor, was born in Scranton, Pennsylvania, on March 31, 1878, the only child of Caroline Conkling McKinstry and Abraham B. McKinstry (1826-1882), a farmer and postmaster. After her father's death, MacKinstry lived in France and Belgium, specifically in Paris from 1892 to 1901 where she studied with the sculptor Auguste Rodin. From 1909 until 1920 she lived with her mother in Buffalo, New York, working there as an artist and teaching art classes; after 1910 the spelling of their last name changed from McKinstry to MacKinstry. She lived and worked in New York City from the mid-twenties to 1938, turning out illustrations for several New York publishing houses, as well as costume designs, decorations, and illustrations for local theater groups. In her later years MacKinstry lived in and around Lenox, Massachusetts, near Emily Howland Leeming Lyman (1871-1951), a friend from Buffalo, and donated her collection of more than 300 illustrated books to the Lenox Library in 1949. Elizabeth MacKinstry died on May 14, 1956, in Pittsfield, Massachusetts, and was buried in Lenox.
MacKinstry's work was exhibited in one-woman shows at the Albright Art Gallery in Buffalo (1922), and in memorial exhibitions at the Lenox Library (1956), in the Central Children's Room of the New York Public Library (1957), and at the Boston Public Library (1958). The April 1957 issue of The Horn Book Magazine was largely devoted to essays on MacKinstry by her colleagues and admirers.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains work by Elizabeth MacKinstry: autograph and typescript versions of poems, a set of illustrations for the children's book Eliza and the Elves, by Rachel Field (New York: Macmillan Company, 1926), and a scrapbook of her original and printed artwork dating from 1924-1934. One volume of poems was bound by John F. Grabau of Buffalo, New York, for MacKinstry's presentation to Emily Howland Leeming Lyman. Also present is a published volume of MacKinstry's poems, Helen's Mirror and Other Verses (London: Elkin Mathews, 1913), issued under her pseudonym Elizabeth Westermain.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Writings, 1904-1957. II. Artwork, 1924-1934.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Children's literature, American -- 20th Century -- Illustrations; Illustration of books -- United States; Illustrators -- United States; Poets, American -- 20th Century; Book jackets -- United States -- 20th Century; Color woodcuts -- United States -- 20th Century; Drawings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Illustrations (layout features) -- United States -- 20th Century; Scrapbooks -- United States -- 20th Century; Illustrators -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Field, Rachel, 1894-1942 ( Eliza and the elves, Illustrations); Grabau, John F., 1878-1948; MacKinstry, E. (Elizabeth); MacKinstry, E. (Elizabeth.) ( Helen's mirror and other verses); Lyman, Emily Howland Leeming, 1871-1951 -- Presentation inscription from Elizabeth MacKinstry; MacKinstry, E. (Elizabeth) -- Presentation inscription to Elizabeth Howland Leeming Lyman
- Writings, 1904-1957; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Custodial History
  Gift of Florence E. Brooks, 1956, unless otherwise identified.
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Writings and Ephemera.
  Scope and Contents
  The series holds autograph manuscripts and typescripts of Elizabeth MacKinstry's poems, most of which she bound in paperboard binders with decorations inside their covers. Also present is a copy of Helen's Mirror and Other Verses (London: Elkin Mathews, 1913), a small volume of poems MacKinstry published under her pseudonym Elizabeth Westermain; it was part of the publisher's "Savile" series of poetry books. Ephemera includes transcribed and clipped published reviews of MacKinstry's books and a postcard advertising an exhibition of MacKinstry's work in 1957.
  - Writings
    - "Dornigen of Brittany," typescript with autograph corrections, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Harlequin of the Jazz Age," typescript with autograph corrections, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Helen's Mirror and Other Verses, with autograph corrections, 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      General
      Laid-in inside front cover: an ink-on-paper drawing of a small girl; pasted in inside back cover: typed transcription of book review from The Bookman, March 1914
    - "In Many Keys," typescript with autograph corrections, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Pygmalion's Feast," typescript with autograph corrections, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "To Aglæades and Other Poems," autograph manuscript with typescript poems inserted, 1904-1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Gift of Elizabeth Leeming Rose, 1970.
      Inscribed by MacKinstry: To Emily Howland Leeming These Poems From "Elizabeth Westermain" - all for Past Memories or Present Love; bound by John F. Graubau of Buffalo, New York
    - "Today at Damascus," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Today at Damascus," autograph manuscript and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Poems; autograph manuscripts and typescripts, 1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ephemera
    - Clipped and typed reviews of MacKinstry's books, 1926, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Postcard announcing an exhibition of MacKinstry's work at the New York Public Library, 1957 April (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Source unknown.
- Artwork, 1924-1934; Series II; 0.58; (3 boxes)
  The series contains a set of ink and watercolor drawings made as illustrations for the children's book Eliza and the Elves by Rachel Field (New York: Macmillan Company, 1926), and a scrapbook kept by MacKinstry. Titled by her "Intimate Journal of Drawings 1924-1934," it contains several hundred drawings, prints, sketches, and printed ephemera affixed to the 156 pages. Media includes ink, pencil, watercolor, colored pencil, colored woodcut, and crayon on paper and card, and includes her experiments in techniques new to her (in particular, reed pen) as well as drawings made for but not used in specific books. MacKinstry also pasted-in printed dust jackets and proofs of illustrations from several projects for which illustrations or decorations were commissioned by New York publishers: Semi-attached, by Anne Parrish (George H. Doran, 1924), Trees, by Joyce Kilmer (George H. Doran, 1925), The Three Owls, by Anne Carroll Moore (Macmillan, 1925), Tales of Laughter, edited by Kate Douglas Wiggin and Nora Archibald Smith (Doubleday, Page, 1926), and Snake Gold by Hervey White (Macmillan, 1926), as well as for her own book of poetry, Puck in Pasture (Doubleday, Page, 1925). Printed ephemera includes letterhead MacKinstry designed for The Coffee Shop in New York City, a clipping from the Academy Notes (Buffalo) about an exhibition of her work, and a clipped cover from The Book Dial, vol. 3, no. 6 (1926), which features her design.
  - Drawings for Eliza and the Elves, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 12-16)
    The set contains 73 drawings on 41 leaves; 70 drawings are ink on paper or card, and 3 are watercolor on card; accompanied by one drawing for an unidentified project.
  - Drawings for Eliza and the Elves, 1926 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 17-18)
  - "Intimate Journal of Drawings"
    - Loose drawings removed from envelope attached to back cover, 1924-1934 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 19)
    - Loose newspaper clippings removed from scrapbook, 1924-1934 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 20)
    - Scrapbook, 1924-1934 (Box 4 (Oversize))